(jazz music)
- We got our start in the early days of the web
as a group of disaffected webmasters
who were using a piece of freely available web software,
but had difficulty with it.
We were fixing bugs.
We were sharing these bug fixes with each other,
like baseball trading cards, if you will,
these patches, as it's called.
And one day we discovered the group
that put out the web server that we were using
basically folded when all their developers left
to go join a brand new company called Netscape.
So a bunch of us decided that,
hey, we're dependent upon this software.
We don't want to become full-time web server developers,
but we want to be able to use this thing
that we've had for free and be able to improve it
and all that kind of stuff.
We looked at the license of the code,
and the license said, here's the software.
Do whatever you want with it.
Don't blame us when it breaks, right?
And we said, hey, that's a pretty good bargain.
Why don't we pass the same bargain
onto the next group of people, right?
So we formed a mailing list, right?
And this was mostly, again, webmasters
and people working at some early internet service providers
or website design companies or places like Amazon
or the internet movie database.
And we combined our patches together
and decided to call it a patchy server for that reason
and went forward.
And really the model of how we worked
was based upon kind of us as a group, as peers,
proposing ideas, vetting each other's ideas and patches
and fixing bugs as a group, as a team.
None of us had met in person, well, some of us had met,
but as a group, we didn't meet in person until 1998,
really three years after we got our start.
And long after, by the way,
we'd become the most predominant web server product
on the planet.
And yet at this time, still, no money, no dime,
not direct to us from this piece of open source software,
but plenty of us made our living
off of building things on top of this piece.
And that's really the story, I think,
of kind of successful open source projects writ large,
which is people working together on common technologies
to solve common problems
so they can go off and make money on other places
or so they can have fun, they can try new ideas,
they can be experimental, right?
And that's really the same story of Apache and of Linux
and all these other open source projects.
- So one of the core things about Apache
is the concept of meritocracy.
Was that a difficult thing to make happen?
I mean, I look at your bylaws and I say,
somebody crafted those bylaws carefully,
or was this just kind of like dumb luck?
Is this just kind of how it worked out?
Were there any like fights over the bylaws,
or did the bylaws just kind of come naturally?
- So let's say you've got a group of your neighbors,
you know, say a four or five block radius, right?
Group of your neighbors, you're on a mailing list, right?
And you kind of wanna be social with each other
because you have to see each other every day.
You know, you don't wanna pick fights necessarily.
But you wanna get something done and you decide that,
hey, let's throw a picnic on some Sunday, right?
So as a group of neighbors, how are you going to decide
how to throw a big group picnic, right?
Well, somebody's gonna say, hey, I have a big grill.
You know, somebody else will say,
I have this great meat place that I go and buy my meat from.
I'll get it there.
Somebody else says, I make a wicked potato salad
or something like that.
And, you know, by people showing up and volunteering things
and saying what they can do
and building upon each other's ideas,
you generally find a way to do it.
That carries a tone of respect for other people's ideas
that, you know, recognizes that passion and motivation
are some of the most finite resources in the world, right?
And you have to cherish that.
You don't wanna, you know,
naysay somebody's idea just out of hand, right?
And so I think it just kind of fell out naturally
from, you know, kind of the golden rule
of do unto others and that kind of thing.
Didn't seem like magic to us, I guess,
when we were doing it.
But yeah, it turns out to be not that hard
to be able to work together
when people have the same common goal,
which is let's build a product
that does all this great stuff.
One thing that we did do that made it easy
to make some of these decisions
was to have a very modular API,
which made it easy for us to be able to say,
"Hey, if you want that special cool feature,
"do it as a separate thing and make it successful,
"and we'll decide whether to bring this into the product
"once it's become successful or not," right?
Another key thing that plays into this
that is true of all open source projects
is that an open source license, like we had on ours,
that Linux has, et cetera,
carries with it something called the right to fork,
which means that if I were to go all Colonel Kurtz
on the project and start saying we're gonna go here
and no one else wanted to follow,
well, all of those other people
could decide to pick up the code
and go start a different project somewhere else
if they couldn't kick me out,
which is probably what they would have tried to do first.
This right to fork means that
you don't have to have any tolerance for dictators.
You don't have to deal with people
who make bad technical decisions.
You can take that future into your hands,
and if you find a group of other people who agree with you,
you can go on and create a new project around it.
So I think that rule, that right to fork,
limits the kind of excesses that we see
whenever we start to talk about
how do groups make decisions and conflict arises,
how do you deal with that conflict?
And it means that your style of leadership
isn't so much one of control
and plotting moves ahead of time,
but instead one of being able to get people on your side,
convince them that you're gonna value their efforts,
value the contributions that they make.
- Tell me a little bit about what you're doing now
and how sort of the Apache work
has flowed into what your current work is.
- Well, I think what we realized
kind of early on with Apache is that
even though we were really carrying forward
the traditions from the Internet Engineering Task Force,
from the BSD community and the Linux communities
in terms of how to write software,
and even though we were using tools
available to the open source world like CVS
and web-based issue trackers and such,
I came to realize that there was a certain kind of,
that if you could define how it was
at Apache Build Software,
define it from the perspective of process
and the perspective of tools,
that was something that if you could
distill it down to a science and make it repeatable,
you could take it to the rest of the software industry.
And you could do that for more open source projects,
brand new ones,
or you could even do it inside of companies.
We, on the outside of big companies like an IBM or an HP,
we tend to think that all those companies
must have that innovation problem licked, right?
They must know how to write software,
great software that maximizes the intellectual capital
that they're paying for every day, right?
Turns out a lot of companies are actually
really bad at getting their engineers,
getting their employees to produce the smartest things,
to reuse each other's work as well as they could,
and as well as the open source community does.
And so I started a company in 1999
on the premise of let's figure this out,
let's put this in a bottle if we can or define it,
and let's take it to the rest of the industry
in the form of a collaboration platform
targeted at version control, issue tracking,
and also capturing the ad hoc, you know,
free form conversation that takes place
in open source projects.
And so part of it is that,
part of it as well is educating communities
on best practices around open source engineering.
How do you have a development process
that is transparent and accessible
to everyone in an organization
rather than something that is, you know,
three people in a cubicle making a decision
about, you know, the right kind of decision,
or a way to implement a particular technical solution, right?
- So finish this sentence, CollabNet is?
- CollabNet is a products and services company
focused on replicating open source collaboration
practices and tools to the rest of the software industry.
- Perfect.
Now we're on.
- Hi there.
I'm here at North Carolina State University
at a meeting hosted by IBM
talking about potential for open source in K-12.
I was very, very fortunate to be on a wonderful panel
with Brian Bellendorf from Apache Foundation.
Brian spoke with the Sakai community last June
in Baltimore as our keynote,
and I was able to talk to Brian
ask him a few things about the beginning of Apache and what he's up to now.